Guide to the United Methodist Church Records, 1784-1984, bulk 1800-1940
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Asbury, Francis, 1745-1816; Coe, William Gwynn; Coke, Thomas, 1747-1814; Purdon, J. H. Colpais (Joseph H.); Methodist Episcopal Church; Methodist Episcopal Church, South; Methodist Episcopal Church. American Mission in North Africa; United Methodist Church (U.S.); Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- History; Methodist Episcopal Church, South. North Carolina Conference; Methodist Episcopal Church, South. Western North Carolina Conference; Methodist Episcopal Church, South. Western North Carolina Conference. Board of Missions and Church Extension; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- History; Methodist Church -- North Carolina -- History -- 18th century; Methodist Church -- North Carolina -- History -- 19th century; Methodist Church -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Methodist Church -- Missions -- Africa; Church architecture -- United States -- North Carolina; Church controversies -- Methodist Church; Methodism; Methodism -- History -- 18th century; Methodism -- History -- 19th century; Methodism -- History -- 20th century; North Carolina -- Religious life and customs; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Alamance County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Ashe County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Bladen County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Burke County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Caswell County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Catawba County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Chatham County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Cleveland County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Dare County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Davidson County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Durham County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Forsyth County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Gates County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- New Hanover County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Iredell County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Lincoln County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Perquimans County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Randolph County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Rowan County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Yadkin County; Methodist Episcopal Church, South -- North Carolina -- Wake County; Race relations -- Christianity -- Methodist Church; Church records and registers -- North Carolina; Minute books; Minutes
Contents of Collection
- National Records Series, 1820-1952,bulk 1908-1939
  Comprises national-level records from the Methodist Episcopal Church (1820-1952) and the Methodist Episcopal Church, South (1857-1939), including correspondence and financial records from the American Mission in North Africa of the Methodist Episcopal Church, 1909-1952. Arranged in two subseries by church name and alphabetically therein.
  - Methodist Episcopal Church Subseries, 1820-1952, bulk 1909-1925
    Comprises primarily American Mission in North Africa correspondence to and from Joseph Cooksey, Edwin Frease, and Joseph Purdon (1909-1925). Also includes a small amount of administrative records from various conferences (1820-1907) and correspondence to and from missionary bishops (1885-1907). Arranged alphabetically.
    - American Mission in North Africa, 1909-1952
      Began in 1908 and was staffed by missionaries of both genders and of a variety of nationalities, including American, English, Irish, German, Algerian, Tunisian, French, Italian, German, and Spanish. Reports for 1911-1912 by all the missionaries can be found in the Official Minutes of the... Annual Meeting of the Mission in North African of the Methodist Episcopal Church, E Pam #240.
      The mission records comprise primarily correspondence to and from Joseph Cooksey, Edwin Frease, and Joseph Purdon (1909-1925), who were mission superintendents in Algiers (Frease) and Tunis (Cooksey followed by Purdon). Subjects in the correspondence include purchases of the New Testament intended for prospective converts as well as for French soldiers; letters to and from the White House on the subject of the appointment of the American Consular Agent at Tunis; correspondence with French authorities; dealings with particular cases (employee relations, pupils from Muslim families, the Boys' School matters in Tunis); Purdon correspondence with The Times (1912-1913); and descriptions of local customs and rituals. Although the correspondence is mainly in English, some letters and documents are in French and Arabic. The mission's records also include contracts, bills, and receipts for the residences of various missionaries, 1914-1952.
      - Correspondence
        - Cooksey, Joseph J., Tunis, 1911-1913, 1923-1925, (5 folders) (Box N1)
        - Frease, Edwin F., Algiers, El-Biar, and Tunis, 1912-1919, (4 folders)
        - Purdon, J. H. C., Tunis, 1909-1919, (1-2 of 50 folders)
        - Purdon, J. H. C., Tunis, 1909-1919, (3-11 of 50 folders) (Box N2)
        - Purdon, J. H. C., Tunis, 1909-1919, (12-22 of 50 folders) (Box N3)
        - Purdon, J. H. C., Tunis, 1909-1919, (23-34 of 50 folders) (Box N4)
        - Purdon, J. H. C., Tunis, 1909-1919, (35-47 of 50 folders) (Box N5)
        - Purdon, J. H. C., Tunis, 1909-1919, (48-50 of 50 folders) (Box N6)
      - Contracts, Bills, Receipts, Tunis, 1914-1952, (4 folders)
    - Licenses to preach, deacon and elder appointments, affirmations of faith, and membership transfers for several conferences 1820-1907
    - Missionary Bishops, Correspondence, 1885-1907
  - Methodist Episcopal Church, South Subseries, 1857-1939, bulk 1908-1939
    Comprises primarily correspondence, minutes, reports, and printed material documenting the planning for the reunification of the MEC and the MECS (1906-1916, 1932-1939), especially hymnal revision. Also includes records for the Methodist Board of Publication, including audits, a catalog, and a report (1885, 1927-1930), as well as reports of the Board of Education (1926) and the Historical Society (1908-1918). Arranged alphabetically. Oversize items have been removed to the Oversize Materials section of this finding aid.
    - Board of Education, annual reports, 1926 (Box N6)
    - Board of Missions, statement by Walter A. Hearn and proceedings against him, 1927 Aug. 5
    - Districts, lists of, approximately 1890s and undated, (2 folders)
    - Historical Society, reports of the historian, 1908-1918
    - Licenses to preach, affirmations of faith, deacon and elder appointments for several conferences, 1857-1932
    - Methodist Board of Publication
      - Audits, 1927-1930, (2 folders)
      - Catalog (Publishing House of the MECS), 1885
      - Report, 1928-1929
    - [Missionary Society, membership certificate, 1857: Removed to Oversize Material, Oversize Folder 1.]
    - Reunification
      - Hymnal revision
        - Correspondence, 1932-1933
        - Matters for decision, 1933 May-July
        - Minutes, 1929, 1932, (1-2 of 4 folders)
        - Minutes, 1929, 1932, (3-4 of 4 folders) (Box N7)
        - Observations on and classifications of hymns, undated
        - Participants, MECS, undated
      - Joint Commission on Methodist Federation, addresses delivered before the commission, 1911 May
      - Joint Commission on Methodist Union, meeting minutes, 1939 Jan. 24-29
      - Judicial Council
        Includes notes made by R. L. Flowers. Copy of photograph of attendees to the General Conference, 1906, removed from this folder to Oversize Material, Oversize Folder 2.
      - Newspaper clipping, How Mulatto Kitty, Slave Girl Who Refused Freedom, Brought About Division of Methodist Church in 1844, Atlanta Constitution Magazine Section, 1916
      - Test case on unification, Clarendon Co., S.C., 1939
      - Uniting Conference, Kansas City, Mo., bulletins, 1939 May 1 and May 10
- Non-N.C. Conference Series, 1806-1910
  Primarily bound volumes of quarterly conference minutes for circuits, charges, and churches in the Baltimore, North Georgia, South Carolina, and Virginia Conferences and other conferences, especially those in Lumpkin Co.; Ga., Marion Co., S.C.; and Gates and Loudoun Cos., Va. Circuit, charge, and church-level records include a classbook of the Pleasant Hill Society (1851-1879, Dallas Co., Ala.); a hand-drawn map from the 1800s of the Holly Springs Circuit (Unknown Co., Miss.); and a history of the formation of the Methodist Protestant Church in Maryland, 1833. There are conference-level records only for the Virginia and Wisconsin Conferences and these include an 1815 list of ministers serving Virginia Conference districts and circuits, as well as a group of hand-written responses of the Eastern Shore of Virginia to the Methodist Episcopal Church split between 1864-1866. Many of the circuits, charges, and churches described in the North Carolina Conference Series were originally part of the South Carolina and Virginia Conferences.
  Arranged in groups alphabetically by conference name, and within each group, by conference, district, and/or circuit, charge, and church records. Within each district name is included a list of the counties represented in the district, as well as a list of the circuits, charges, and churches in this collection that were in that district. Circuit, charge, and church records are organized by county name. The names of districts represented in the circuit, charge, and church records in this series, but for which there are no district records, are also listed in the district grouping in this series. Oversize items have been removed to the Oversize Materials section of this finding aid.
  - Alabama, 1851-1879 (Box NNC1)
    - Circuit, Charge, and Church Records
      - Dallas Co., 1851-1879
        - Pleasant Hill Circuit, Unknown District, 1851-1879
          - Classbook of the Pleasant Hill Society, 1851-1879(M-6464)
  - Baltimore, 1863-1901 (Box NNC1)
    - District Records
      - [Rockingham District: No district-level records]
        Counties represented in the Rockingham District: Unknown.
        Circuits, charges, and/or churches found in this collection that were in the Rockingham District: Bridgewater Circuit; Rockingham Circuit; and Upper Rockingham Circuit.
      - [Winchester District: No district-level records]
        Counties represented in the Winchester District: Unknown.
        Circuits, charges, and/or churches found in this collection that were in the Winchester District: Jefferson Circuit.
    - Circuit, Charge, and Church Records
      - Unknown Co., 1863-1874, 1899-1901
        - Bridgewater Circuit (MEC and MECS), Rockingham District, 1864-1874
          - Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1864-1874
            Includes list of district presiding elders, 1863-1907; list of circuit ministers, 1863-1908; minutes of meetings of parsonage trustees, 1897; and accounts of P. Herring, 1849-1859.
        - Jefferson Circuit, Winchester District, W.Va., 1899-1901
          - Record of Twentieth Century Thank Offerings, 1899-1901(M-2981)
        - Rockingham Circuit, Rockingham District, 1863
          - [Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1863: Found in Baltimore Conference, Unknown Co., Bridgewater Circuit, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1864-1874.]
        - Upper Rockingham Circuit, Rockingham District, 1863
          - [Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1863: Found in Baltimore Conference, Unknown Co., Bridgewater Circuit, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1864-1874.]
  - Georgia, 1830-1866 (Box NNC1)
    - District Records
      - [Dahlonega District: No district-level records]
        Counties represented in the Dahlonega District: Lumpkin.
        Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Dahlonega District: Dahlonega Circuit/Station.
    - Circuit, Charge, and Church Records
      - Carroll Co., 1830-1846
        - Carronton Mission (MEC), Unknown district, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1830-1846
      - Lumpkin Co., 1861-1863, 1866
        - [Dahlonega Circuit/Station, Dahlonega District, 1861-1863, 1866: Found in North Georgia Conference, Lumpkin Co., Dahlonega and Jones Chapel, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1861-1878.]
  - Kentucky, 1809-1867 (Box NNC1A)
    - Circuit, Charge, and Church Records
      - Fayette Co.
        - Lexington First Church, Board of Trustees Minutes, 1809-1867
  - Maryland, 1833 (Box NNC1)
    - Conference Records
      - History of formation of the Methodist Protestant Church, 1833
  - Mississippi, 1800s
    - Circuit, Charge, and Church Records
      - Various districts: Biloxi, Choctaw, Covington, Paulding, Pearl River, Mt. Carmel, and Seashore Districts; Mt. Carmel, Westville, and White Sand Circuits
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1835-1877 (312 pp.) (Box NNC1-B)
      - Holly Springs Circuit, unknown district
        - Hand-drawn map, 1800s Mar. 14 (Box NNC1)
          Includes description of town of Memphis, [Miss.?].
  - North Georgia, 1867-1878 (Box NNC1)
    - District Records
      - [Dahlonega District: No district-level records]
        Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Dahlonega District: Dahlonega Circuit/Station/Mission; Dahlonega and Auraria Station; and Dahlonega and Jones Chapel Circuit/Station.
    - Circuit, Charge, and Church Records
      - Lumpkin Co., 1867-1878
        - [Dahlonega Circuit/Station/Mission, Dahlonega District, 1869-1873: Found in North Georgia Conference, Lumpkin Co., Dahlonega and Jones Chapel, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1861-1878.]
        - [Dahlonega and Auraria Station, Dahlonega District, 1867-1868: Found in North Georgia Conference, Lumpkin Co., Dahlonega and Jones Chapel, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1861-1878.]
        - Dahlonega and Jones Chapel Circuit/Station, multiple districts, 1874-1878
          At least 1861-1866: Circuit in Dahlonega District, Ga. Conference
          1867-1873: Circuit in Dahlonega District, North Ga. Conference
          1874-1875: Circuit in Gainesville District, North Ga. Conference
          1876-at least 1878: Churches in Dahlonega District, North Ga. Conference
          - [Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1874-1878 (L-2706 and one folder): Bound volume removed to Oversize Materials, Oversize Box 1.]
  - South Carolina, 1807-1873 (Box NNC1)
    - District Records
      - [Camden District: No district records]
        Counties represented in the Camden District: Unknown.
        Circuits, charges, and/or churches found in this collection that were in the Camden District: Montgomery Circuit and Rocky River Circuit.
      - [Catawba District: No district records. See also the N.C. Conference.]
        Counties represented in the Catawba District: Lincoln, N.C., and Unknown.
        Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Catawba District: Lincolnton Circuit (N.C.); Montgomery Circuit; and Rocky River Circuit.
      - [Cheraw District: No district records]
        Counties represented in the Cheraw District: Unknown.
        Circutis, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Cheraw District: Wadesboro Circuit.
      - [Fayetteville District: No district records. Primarily found in the N.C. Conference.]
        Counties represented in the Fayetteville District: Unknown.
        Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Fayetteville District: Wadesboro Circuit.
      - [Lincolnton District: No district records. Found in the N.C. Conference.]
      - [Marion District: No district records]
        Counties represented in the Marion District: Marion County.
        Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Marion District: Bennettsville Circuit.
      - [Spartanburg District: No district records. Found in the N.C. Conference.]
    - Circuit, Charge, and Church Records
      - Marion Co., 1846-1873
        - Bennettsville Circuit, Marion District, 1846-1873
          - Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1846-1873(L-5704)
      - Unknown Co., 1807-1819, 1845, 1849
        - [Montgomery Circuit (MEC), multiple districts, 1808: Found in South Carolina Conference, Unknown Co., Rocky River Circuit.]
          - Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1808
        - Rocky River Circuit (MEC), multiple districts, 1807-1819
          Circuit in Camden and Catawba Districts.
          - Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1807-1819
            Includes Montgomery Circuit, 1808.
        - Wadesboro Circuit, multiple districts, 1845, 1849
          Circuit in Cheraw and Fayetteville Districts.
          - Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1845, 1849
  - Virginia, 1806-1910, bulk 1817-1872 (Box NNC1)
    - Conference Records
      - Board of Education, minutes, 1902-1910(M-2927)
      - Ministers serving districts and circuits (MEC), 1815
      - Minutes, 1806-1808
      - Responses of eastern shore of Va. to Methodist Episcopal church split, 1864-1866 (See also the Historical Sketches Series, Ministers Subseries, Coe, William Gwynn.)
    - District Records
      - [Fredericksburg District: No district records]
        Counties represented in the Fredericksburg District: Loudoun County.
        Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Fredericksburg District: Loudoun Circuit.
      - [Murfreesboro District: No district records. Found in the N.C. Conference.]
      - [Norfolk District: No district records. Found in the N.C. Conference.]
      - [Norfolk and Murfreesboro District: No district records. Found in the N.C. Conference. See either the Norfolk or the Murfreesboro Districts.]
      - [Suffolk District: No district records. Primarily found in the N.C. Conference.]
        Counties represented in the Suffolk District: Gates County.
        Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Suffolk District: Gates Circuit.
      - [Washington District: No district records]
        Counties represented in the Washington District: Loudoun County.
        Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Washington District: Loudoun Circuit.
      - [Yadkin District: No district records. Found in the N.C. Conference.]
    - Circuit, Charge, and Church Records
      - Loudoun Co., 1850-1858
        - Loudoun Circuit, multiple districts, 1850-1858
          1850-1852: Circuit in Fredericksburg District
          1853-1858: Circuit in Washington District
          - Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1850-1858(M-2929)
      - Unknown Co., 1854-1856
        - Pittsylvania Circuit, Unknown District, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1854-1856
  - Wisconsin, 1848-1849 (Box NNC1)
    - Conference Records
      - Annual Conference, minutes of first session (typescript of original), (MEC), 1848-1849
- N.C. Conference Records Series, 1784-1974, bulk 1838-1939
  Comprises primarily bound volumes of quarterly conference minutes that document the administrative life of circuits, charges, churches, missions, and stations of the N.C. Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South (MECS) in the eastern and central counties of North Carolina, particularly Bladen, Caswell, Chatham, Dare, Durham, Gates, New Hanover, Perquimans, and Wake, but also including other counties (1784-1974). The series also includes bound journals of annual conference meetings for the N.C. Conference of the MECS (1838-1913) as well as bound volumes of district conference minutes and quarterly conference minutes for, among other districts, the Durham, Elizabeth City, Raleigh, and Wilmington Districts of the N.C. Conference of the MECS (1866-1939). There is some overlap with the Western N.C. Conference. All records are MECS unless noted otherwise by the abbreviations MEC for Methodist Episcopal Church and MC for Methodist Church. Arranged in three subseries: Conference Records, District Records, and Circuit, Charge, and Church Records.
  - Conference Records Subseries (Restricted), 1812-1953, bulk 1838-1931
    Comprises primarily the bound journals, both originals and copies, recording the annual conference meetings (1838-1913) of the N.C. Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South (MECS). Also includes conference statistics (1886-1899); records from trials of ministers (1885-1901); and minutes, reports, and financial and legal documents for the Board of Education (1910-1930), Board of Trustees (1848-1953), the Relief Society (1838-1847), and the Raleigh Advocate Publishing Co. (1879-1919). There are a few records for the N.C. Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church and Methodist Church. These are noted by the abbreviations MEC and MC. Arranged alphabetically. Oversize materials have been removed to the Oversize Materials section of this finding aid.
    Patrons must use copies of journals and then consult originals if required.
    - Account Book, 1887 (M-2724) (Box NCC1)
      Includes a report on the standing of Trinity College.
    - Board of Education
      - Minute Book, 1911-1930, and Ledger, 1910-1930(M-6911)
      - Staff report (MC), 1952-1953
    - Board of Trustees minutes, 1848-1957(M-6916)
    - [Conference attendees, photograph, including names, 1887 (51st annual conference): Removed to Oversize Materials, Oversize Folder 3.]
    - Conference Statistics
      - 1886-1889(M-2738)
      - 1894-1897(M-2739)
      - 1900-1903(M-2741) (Box NCC2)
    - Duke Endowment Superannuate Fund, letters of thanks to W. P. Few, 1915-1932, (2 folders)
    - Journals
      [Patrons must use copies of Journals for 1838-1885 and then consult the originals if required.]
      - Xerox copies
        - 1838-1842(M-7031) (Box NCC3)
          Copy of original volumes L-2725 and part of L-2726, found in box NCC8.
        - 1843-1848(M-7032)
          Copy of parts of original volumes L-2726 and F-2727, found in boxes NCC8 and NCC9.
        - 1849-1852(M-7033)
          Copy of part of original volume F-2727, found in box NCC9.
        - 1853-1855(M-7034)
        - 1856-1858(M-7035)
        - 1859-1862(M-7036) (Box NCC4)
        - 1863-1866(M-7037)
        - 1867-1868(M-7038)
          Copy of part of original volume F-2728, found in box NCC10.
        - 1869-1870(M-7039)
        - 1871-1872(M-7040)
        - 1873-1874(M-7041) (Box NCC5)
          Copy of part of original volumes F-2728 and F-2729, found in boxes NCC10 and NCC11.
        - 1875-1876(M-7042)
          Copy of part of original volume F-2729, found in box NCC11.
        - 1877(M-7043)
        - 1878(M-7044)
          Copy of part of original volume F-2729 found in box NCC11.
        - 1879(M-7045)
        - 1880(M-7046) (Box NCC6)
        - 1881(M-7047)
        - 1882(M-7048)
          Copy of part of original volume F-2730, found in box NCC12.
        - 1883(M-7049)
        - 1884(M-7050)
        - 1885(M-7051) (Box NCC7)
      - Originals
        Patrons must use copies of Journals for 1838-1885 and then consult the originals if required.
        - 1838-1842(L-2725) (Box NCC8)
          Original of xerox copy, found in box NCC3. Also available on microfilm.
        - 1840-1846(L-2726)
        - 1846-1866(F-2727) (Box NCC9)
          Original of xerox copy, found in boxes NCC3 and NCC4. Also available on microfilm.
        - 1867-1873(F-2728) (Box NCC10)
          Original of xerox copy, found in box NCC4. Also available on microfilm.
        - 1874-1881(F-2729) (Box NCC11)
          Original of xerox copy, found in boxes NCC4 and NCC5.
        - 1882-1885(F-2730) (Box NCC12)
          Original of xerox copy, found in box NCC6. Also available on microfilm.
        - 1886-1889(F-2731) (Box NCC13)
        - 1890-1893(F-2732) (Box NCC14)